A Finding Aid to the Institute of Contemporary Arts Records, 1927-circa 1985, bulk 1947-1967, in the Archives of American Art AAA.instcona
Archives of American Art
Institute of Contemporary Arts records
bulk 1947-1967
1927-circa 1985
AAA.instcona
Archives of American Art
36 Linear feet
The records of the Washington, D.C. arts and educational organization, Institute of Contemporary Arts, measure 36 linear feet and date from 1927-circa 1985, with the bulk of the material spanning the organization's active years, 1947-1967. The collection documents the arts and cultural programming organized by the ICA through correspondence, artists' files, program and exhibition files, administrative and financial records, printed materials and photographs. Also found are administrative, student, and teacher records of the ICA school; records of the Fine Arts Committee of the People-to-People Project; and some personal papers of the ICA's founder, Robert Richman.
Institute of Contemporary Arts. (Washington, D.C.)
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 9 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1937, 1944-1980 (2.7 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 2: Artists' Files, 1943-1967, 1970-1979 (4.9 linear feet; Boxes 3-8)
Series 3: ICA Program Files, circa 1947-1968 (5.2 linear feet; Boxes 8-13, 27)
Series 4: Organizations, 1927, 1940s-1967 (7.3 linear feet; Boxes 13-20, OV 39)
Series 5: ICA School Files, 1945-1953 (7.0 linear feet; Boxes 21-27)
Series 6: Administrative and Financial Files, 1945-1979, 1983 (5.2 linear feet; Boxes 28-33, 38)
Series 7: Printed Materials, 1945-1970 (2.9 linear feet; Boxes 33-35, 38)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1930s-1960s, circa 1985 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 35-36)
Series 9: Personal Papers of Robert Richman, 1940s-1980 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 36-37)
Biographical/Historical note
The Washington, D.C. arts and educational organization, Institute of Contemporary Arts (ICA), was founded by poet Robert Richman in 1947 to bring arts and culture to the nation's capital. The school, originally named the King-Smith School of Creative Arts, was redesigned and renamed Institute of Contemporary Arts by Richman in 1948. The school's philosophy was based on Sir Herbert Read's Education Through Art, and provided professional training in painting, sculpture, literature, music, and theater. In addition, the ICA operated an evening school and brought prominent artists and literary figures to the nation's capital for exhibitions, concerts, workshops, lectures, readings, and performances. Teachers at the school included potter Alexander Giampietro, sculptor David Aaron, designers Beatrice Takeuchi and Hubert Leckie, and painter Kenneth Noland.
The school closed in August 1951, but the ICA continued to provide an impressive roster of programs and performances held at the Corcoran Gallery of Art and other D.C. institutions, such as exhibitions by Naum Gabo, Bernard Leach, Isamu Noguchi, and Hans Richter; readings by W.H. Auden, T.S. Eliot, Katherine Anne Porter, and Dylan Thomas; lectures by Charles Eames, Aldous Huxley, Octavio Paz, and Frank Lloyd Wright; and performances by Aaron Copland, Paul Hindemith, José Limón Dance Company, and Ravi Shankar. The organization also sponsored visiting professorships for international artists and writers, such as Nadine Gordimer, and hosted an annual Congress of Artists and Writers from 1959-1964.
In the late 1950s and early 1960s, the ICA was successful in securing some large grants to continue and expand its programming and to secure permanent space at the Meridian House Foundation. However, by the late 1960s the organization's programming declined.
ICA founder Robert Richman was a poet and literary editor at New Republic magazine in the early 1950s. He was active in the arts community in D.C. and in international exchange organizations, including the Fine Arts Committee of the People-to-People Project, an initiative started by President Dwight D. Eisenhower in the late 1950s. Robert Richman passed away in 1987.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Institute of Contemporary Arts records were donated by Maida Richman, the wife of the ICA's founder, Robert Richman, in 1986.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Washington, D.C. arts and educational organization, Institute of Contemporary Arts, measure 36 linear feet and date from 1927-circa 1985, with the bulk of the material spanning the organization's active years, 1947-1967. The collection documents the arts and cultural programming organized by the ICA through correspondence, artists' files, program and exhibition files, administrative and financial records, printed materials and photographs. Also found are administrative, student, and teacher records of the ICA school; records of the Fine Arts Committee of the People-to-People Project; and some personal papers of the ICA's founder, Robert Richman.
Robert Richman's professional and personal relationships with numerous artists and writers which the ICA hosted in D.C. are documented in Correspondence and Artists' Files. Correspondence files include letters from Joseph and Anni Albers, Alfred Barr, e.e. cummings, Alexander Giampietro, Naum Gabo, Walter Gropius, Erick Hawkins, Duncan Phillips, Hans Richter, Kay Sage and Yves Tanguy, and William Carlos Williams. Also found is correspondence with benefactors, board members, and arts organizations regarding exhibitions and administrative details; and with teachers and the Veteran's Administration regarding school issues.
Artists' Files contains mostly incoming and outgoing correspondence, but also found are biographies, exhibition printed materials, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings and scattered portrait photographs. Of interest are files on Aaron Copland, e.e. cummings, T.S. Eliot, Wojciech Fangor, Nadine Gordimer, Robert Graves, Aldous Huxley, Janheinz Jahn, Kathleen Raine, and Sir Herbert Read.
In addition to Correspondence and Artists' Files, materials regarding ICA's programming, such as correspondence with artists and galleries, press releases, shipping records, financial records, printed materials, photographs, inventory and price lists, are found in ICA Program Files.
The ICA and Robert Richman collaborated with numerous arts and international exchange organizations to organize exhibitions, performances, symposium, and to host visiting artists. Materials regarding such collaborations are found in Organizations and includes correspondence, scattered financial records, notes, and printed materials such as bulletins, brochures, schedules, reports, and press releases. This series also includes substantial material related to the Fine Arts Committee of the People-to-People Program, an international exchange initiative of President Dwight D. Eisenhower begun in 1956.
The school's records include correspondence, notebooks (attendance books), teacher files documenting classes and grades, extensive student files and student enrollment cards, mailing lists, class cards, and notes for classes taught by Robert Richman.
Administrative and Financial Files include accounting and banking records, budgets, founding documents, fundraising records, grants records, mailing lists, membership lists, and Meridian House Foundation records.
ICA's programs are also documented by comprehensive printed materials arranged by ICA seasons, 1947-1967. Printed materials include program calendars, exhibition announcements, invitations, membership forms, and press releases. Also found are newspaper clippings and three oversized clippings scrapbooks.
Photographs include black and white photographs and negatives of people, most of whom are unidentified. Robert Richman's personal papers includes personal correspondence, correspondence related to "New Republic," handwritten and typed writings, some bills, and his curriculum vitae.
Unrepresented in this collection are records of ICA's ICONART Collection (Contemporary Arts Archives), an archive of films and tapes of artists' performances, lectures and events held by ICA.
Albers, Anni; Albers, Josef; Barr, Alfred H., Jr., 1902-1981; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Cummings, E. E., (Edward Estlin), 1894-1962; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Fangor, Wojciech, 1922-; Gabo, Naum, 1890-1977; Giampietro, Alexander; Gordimer, Nadine; Graves, Robert; Gropius, Walter, 1883-1969; Hawkins, Erick; Huxley, Aldous, 1894-1963; Jahn, Janheinz; Meridian House Foundation.; People-to-People. (Organization); Phillips, Duncan, 1886-1966; Raine, Kathleen, 1908-2003; Read, Herbert Edward, Sir, 1893-1968; Richman, Robert; Richter, Hans, 1888-1976; Sage, Kay; Tanguy, Yves, 1900-1955; United States. Veterans Administration.; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963; Art -- Societies, etc. -- Washington (D.C.); Photographs; School records; Scrapbooks
- Correspondence, 1937; 1944-1980; Series 1; 2.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  1.1 Alphabetical, 1945-1969, circa 1975-1978
  1.2 Chronological, 1937, 1944-1980
  - Alphabetical, 1945-1969; circa 1975-1978; 1.1
    Folders are arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name.
    Scope and Contents note
    The incoming and outgoing correspondence is a mix of professional and personal in nature, the bulk of which dates from 1945-1965. Correspondence is often regarding organizing exhibitions and arranging visits to D.C., the school, administrative affairs, Richman's poetry, and his work at "New Republic." Correspondents are mostly artists, writers, friends, colleagues, collaborating organizations, benefactors, dignitaries and others. Of interest is correspondence with Alexander Giampietro, Naum Gabo, Erick Hawkins, Duncan Phillips, and Hans Richter.
    - A, Miscellaneous, 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B, Miscellaneous, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - C, Miscellaneous, 1947-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - D, Miscellaneous, 1945-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - E, Miscellaneous, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - F, Miscellaneous, 1945-1955; 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - G, Miscellaneous, 1961-1969; 1946-1957; 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - H, Miscellaneous, 1946-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Holiday Cards, circa 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - I-J, Miscellaneous, 1947-1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Invitations, Diplomats, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Invitations, President Kennedy and President Johnson, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Johnson, President Lyndon and Lady Bird, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - K-L, Miscellaneous, 1977; 1947-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - M, Miscellaneous, 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - N, Miscellaneous, 1951-1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - O-P, Miscellaneous, 1947-1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Q-R, Miscellaneous, circa 1975; 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Richman, Robert, European Trip, 1964; 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
    - Richman, Robert, European Trip, 1964-1965; 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - S, Miscellaneous, 1976-1978; 1948-1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - T-V, Miscellaneous, 1947-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - W, Miscellaneous, 1948-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - X-Z, Miscellaneous, circa 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chronological, 1937; 1944-1980; 1.2
    Folders are arranged chronologically.
    Found is incoming and outgoing correspondence related to the school and ICA's programming, including correspondence with teachers, the Veteran's Administration, board members, and artists regarding arrangements for exhibitions and guest lectures. Of interest is limited correspondence from Joseph and Anni Albers, Alfred Barr, e.e. cummings, Walter Gropius, Kay Sage and Yves Tanguy, and William Carlos Williams. Draft letters, notes, meeting notes, contracts and financial records are scattered throughout. The bulk of the correspondence dates from 1948-1955.
    - Chronological, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chronological, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chronological, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chronological, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chronological, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - Chronological, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Chronological [Summer 1949], 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chronological, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Chronological, 1950; 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
    - Chronological, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
    - Chronological, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Chronological, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Chronological, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Chronological, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Chronological (1954), 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - Chronological (1955), 1950-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Chronological, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Chronological, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Chronological, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Chronological, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Chronological, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Chronological, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Chronological, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Chronological, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Chronological, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    - Chronological, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Chronological, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Chronological, 1965; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Chronological, 1970-1977; 1980 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Artists' Files, 1943-1967; 1970-1979; Series 2; 4.9 Linear feet Boxes 3-8
  Artists' Files contains mostly incoming and outgoing correspondence with artists, authors, poets, musicians, composers, choreographers, and others, regarding arrangements of ICA-sponsored performances, lectures, and visiting professorships. Also found are biographies, exhibition printed materials, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings and scattered portrait photographs. Of interest are files on Nadia Boulanger, Aaron Copeland, e.e. cummings, T.S. Eliot, and Aldous Huxley, as well as lecture tour files for Wojciech Fangor, Nadine Gordimer, Robert Graves, Janheinz Jahn, Kathleen Raine, and Sir Herbert Read. The bulk of the materials date from 1943-mid-1960s.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by artist's last name.
  - Albers, Joseph and Anni, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Auden, W.H., 1946-1954 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Barker, George, IEP Lecture Tour, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 28-32)
  - Bartra, Agusti, Lecture Tour, 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
  - Bayer, Herbert, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Beckett, Samuel, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Beer, Abraham, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Bellow, Saul, 1954-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ben-Haim, Paul, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bentley, Eric, circa 1947-1958 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Berlin, Isaiah, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bernstein, Leonard, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Berryman, John, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Betjeman, John, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bich, Nguyen Ngoc, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Biddle, George, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Bihalji-Merin, Otto, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Blackmur, Richard, 1949-1950; 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Bogan, Louise, 1949-1950; 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bonnefoy, Yves, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Borges, Jorge Luis, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Bosquet, Alain, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Boulanger, Nadia, 1956-1965 (Box 4, Folder 22-27)
  - Bowen, Elizabeth, 1953-1961 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Bowers, Faubion, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Britten, Benjamin, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Brogan, Denis, 1957-1964 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Brower, Reuben, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Brun, Herbert, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Buber, Martin, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Butler, Reginald, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Cahill, James, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Calder, Alexander, 1957; 1964; circa 1949-1951 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Campbell, Joseph, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Camus, Albert, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Candela, Felix, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Capote, Truman, 1954-1962 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Carter, Elliott, 1959-1964 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Cary, Joyce, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Char, René, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Chavez, Carlos, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Cheever, John, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Chen, Chi-Ying, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ciardi, John, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Clark, Kenneth, Sir, 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Coleman, Elliott, 1957-1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Colum, Padraic, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Conquest, Robert, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Conrad, Doda, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cooke, Alistair, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cooper, Douglas, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Copeland, Aaron, 1955-1961; 1946 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Cravo, Mario, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Crosby, John, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Cummings, E.E., 1950-1962 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Cunningham, Merce, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Curnow, Allen, Lecture Tour, 1960-1966; 1950 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - Daiches, David, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Dallapiccola, Luigi, 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - D'Arcy, Martin, 1957-1963 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Datta, Rajeshwari, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Day-Lewis, C., Lecture Tour, 1956-1961 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Dineson, Isak, Lecture Tour, circa 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
  - Doderer, Heimito von, 1961-1962; 1950s (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Dorfles, Gillo, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Dos Passos, John, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Douglas, William O., Justice, 1954-1964 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Doxiadis, C.A., 1959-1964 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Duchamp, Marcel, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Dugan, Alan, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Duncan, Robert, 1961-1962; 1967 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Durrell, Lawrence, 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Dutilleux, Henri, 1959-1965 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Eames, Charles, 1956-1967 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Eberhart, Richard, 1950-1964 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Edmunds, John, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Ede, H.S., 1949-1960, undated (Box 5, Folder 40-42)
  - Eliade, Mircea, 1956-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Eliot, T.S., 1946-1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ellison, Ralph, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Emmanuel, Pierre, Lecture Tour, 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Engle, Paul, 1955-1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Evans, Walker, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fagg, William, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Fangor, Wojciech, Lecture Tour, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  - Farleigh, John, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Faulkner, William, 1955-1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Forster, E.M., 1947 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Fowlie, Wallace, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Frank, Joseph, 1955-1956 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Friar, Kimon, 1959-1964 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Frith, Clifford, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Fromm, Erich, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Frost, Robert, 1952-1963 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Fry, Christopher, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Fukuzawa, Ichiro, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Fuller, Albert, 1956-1961 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Fuller, Buckminster, 1961-1964 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Gordimer, Nadine, Lecture Tour, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 24-26)
  - Graham, Martha, 1966; 1959-1963 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Graves, Robert, Lecture Tour, 1956-1963 (Box 6, Folder 28-31)
  - H.D. (Hilda Doolittle), 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Huxley, Aldous, 1952-1963 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Jahn, Janheinz, Lecture Tour, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Jahn, Janheinz, Lecture Tour, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Krige, Uys, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Leach, Bernard, 1949-1960; 1970-1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Lehmann, Rosamond, 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
  - Lippmann, Walter, 1963; 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Lowell, Robert, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Maciver, Loren, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Madariaga, Salvador de, Lecture Tour, 1956-1961 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
  - Man Ray, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Miró, Joán, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1949-1954 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1948-1954; 1963 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Nin, Anaïs, circa 1948 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Paz, Octavio, Lecture Tour, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 19-20)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Radhakrishnan, Sarvepalli, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Raine, Kathleen, 1952, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Raine, Kathleen, Lecture Tour, 1956-1962 (Box 7, Folder 24-26)
  - Ransome, John Crowe, 1947-1957 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Read, Herbert, Sir, Lecture Tour, 1948-1960 (Box 7, Folder 28-30)
  - Read, Herbert, Sir, Lecture Tour, 1959-1964 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Read, John, Lecture Tour, 1958-1963 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Schwartz, Delmore, 1953-1955; 1947 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Seferis, George, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Shankar, Ravi, circa 1961 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Snow, C.P., Lord, 1978; 1955-1967 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Snyder, Robert, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Tate, Allen, 1946-1951 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Thomas, Dylan (and Edith Sitwell), 1953, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Toynbee, Arnold, 1960-1963; 1948 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Wain, John, Lecture Tour, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Wilson, Colin, Lecture Tour, 1960-1964 (Box 8, Folder 16-18)
  - Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1943-1949 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified Artists, 1954, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Various American Painters, Biographical Information, circa 1964 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Various Latin American Artists, 1961-1965 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- ICA Program Files, circa 1947-1968; Series 3; 5.2 Linear feet Boxes 8-13, 27
  Program Files contain materials regarding the organization of exhibitions, performances, symposiums, and other programs organized by ICA, including the annual Congress of Artists and Writers, and University Consortium. Materials include correspondence with artists and galleries, press releases, shipping records, financial records, printed materials, photographs, inventory and price lists. There is extensive material regarding Bernard Leach's traveling exhibition and publication "A Potter's Portfolio."
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - 1951-1952 Films, Chamber Concerts, Dances (Limón, Dean, Destine) (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - 1952-1953 Series (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Abstract Art in Ancient Textiles, 1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - American Indian Show, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - [American Indian Show?], Department of Interior, Lee Udall, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - American Indian Sipapu Exhibition, 1965-1967 (Box 8, Folder 28-31)
  - "American Painting - Survey 1964" Exhibition, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 32-33)
  - "Art Books From Italy" Exhibition, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - "Art in Washington 1964" Exhibition (Jan. 29 - Mar. 1, 1965), 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 35-36)
  - Asian Paintings Exhibition, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Balasarasvati, 1965, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Bertoia, Harry, Recent Works Exhibition, 1957; 1967 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Burundi Royal Drummers and Dancers, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Burundi Royal Drummers and Dancers (Oct. 19-20, 1964), 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Chile Ballet, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The Classics in 1960 Symposium, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Cocteau, Jean, Exhibition, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Congress for Cultural Freedom, Stephen Spender, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Congress of Artists and Writers (1st-4th: 1959-1962) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Congress of Artists and Writers (1st: 1959), circa 1958-1960 (Box 9, Folder 12-24)
  - Congress of Artists and Writers (2nd: 1960), 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 25-30)
  - Congress of Artists and Writers (3rd: 1961), 1956; 1960-1961 (Box 9, Folder 31-32)
  - Congress of Artists and Writers (4th: 1962) (Box 9, Folder 33)